Guide to the Mel Rosenthal photographs, 1975-2011 RL.10011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mel Rosenthal photographs
1975-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rosenthal, Mel, 1940-
RL.10011
3 Linear Feet 6 boxes Approximately 92 items
Collection consists of 80 black-and-white photographs taken by native New Yorker Mel Rosenthal, stemming from two documentary projects. The first documents the destruction by arson of an entire South Bronx neighborhood in New York City in the 1970s, with images of burned-out buildings and inhabitants who were forced to abandon their homes. The second project depicts Arab Americans, including men, women and children of Syrian, Egyptian, Moroccan, Algerian, Jordanian and Palestinian descent, living in New York State during the last decade of the 20th century and the early 2000s. Scenes include images of children, professionals, neighborhood life, and the religious lives of Christians, Muslims, Greek Orthodox, Maronites, Jews and Coptics. The gelatin silver prints measure 11x14 and 16x20 inches. Also included are some publicity items for exhibits and a workshop on documentary photography, and an audiocassette recording of Rosenthal speaking at an exhibit opening in 2004. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Biographical Note
Mel Rosenthal (1940-2017) was a documentary photographer based in New York City and director of photographic programs at SUNY-Empire State beginning in 1975. Born in the Bronx, his family moved to South Carolina for a time but returned to the Bronx where he grew3 up. He is best known for his images taken in his old neighborhood. He published In the South Bronx of America in 2000.
Always interested in refugees and immigrants and how they managed life in the United States, he started a project around 2000 about the experiences of Arab Americans, and exhibited the portraits shortly afer the 2001 terrorist attacks partly in an effort to counteract blind prejudice against them.
Rosenthal received degrees from City College and the University of Connecticut, and he first took up the camera professionally as a medical photographer in Tanzania. Subsequently, his photography mainly focused on his home base in New York City. However, other projects took him to other U.S. states, and to Vietnam, Cuba, Nicaragua, and Puerto Rico. He died in New York City in 2017.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Reproductions may only be made for personal use; all other uses, including publication and exhibition, require permission from the estate. The original audiocassette recording is closed to use; a copy must be made for access.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Alternate Form of Material
An online exhibit of selected Rosenthal images from the South Bronx is available for viewing through the Duke University Libraries exhibits website.
Provenance
The Mel Rosenthal photographs were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2004 and 2008.
Related Material
Culturefront (serial)
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Collection Overview
Collection consists of 80 black-and-white photographs taken by New York City native Mel Rosenthal, stemming from two documentary projects. The first documents the destruction by arson of an entire South Bronx neighborhood in New York City in the 1970s, with images of burned-out buildings and inhabitants who were forced to abandon their homes. The neighborhood is the same one where Rosenthal grew up, and the series features a portrait of Mel Rosenthal in his old bedroom.
The second project examines the daily lives of Arab Americans, including men, women and children of Syrian, Egyptian, Moroccan, Algerian, Jordanian and Palestinian descent, in New York State in the early 2000s. Scenes include images of children, professionals, neighborhood life, and the religious lives of Christians, Muslims, Greek Orthodox, Maronites, Jews and Coptics. It was exhibited shortly after the 2001 terrorist attacks.
Selected images in the Rosenthal collection were exhibited at Duke University and these available online. The gelatin silver prints measure 11x14 and 16x20 inches. Exhibit prints in their mats measure 16x20 and 20x24 inches.
Also included are some publicity items for exhibits and workshops on documentary photography, a music CD with photography by Rosenthal, and an audiocassette recording of Rosenthal speaking at an exhibit opening in 2004.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arab Americans -- New York; Arab Americans -- Portraits; Bronx (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs; Documentary Photography -- New York; Photography of immigrants; Refugees -- New York; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001 -- Influence; Bronx (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs; Bronx (New York, N.Y.) -- Social conditions; New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs; Audiocassettes; Audio recordings.; Black-and-white photographs; CD-ROMs; Gelatin silver prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Rosenthal, Mel, 1940-
- In the South Bronx of America, 1975-1983, 2004; 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Comprises 33 black-and-white photographs documenting the destruction in the South Bronx by fire, 1975-1983. Most matted prints measure 16x20" (boxes 1 and 2), but two prints measure 20x24" (box 3). Original captions have been retained as well as narrative comments by photographer; captions for untitled prints have been supplied by library staff and are in brackets.
  - [Gutted buildings with demolition site in foreground] (Box 3, Image RL10011-P-0001)
    I was born and grew up in what is now called the South Bronx. After twenty years away, I returned in 1975, to a neighborhood in ruins. The sturdy well-constructed buildings that had once housed tens of thousands of people were gutted and burned out.
  - South of the Cross Bronx Expressway (Box 1, Image RL00011-P-0002)
    New York's Department of Housing Preservation and Development may have been competing for the Potemkin Prize last summer [1983], when it announced a plan to mount decals in the broken windows and empty frames of all the hundreds of burnt-out and sealed-up buildings that line the Cross Bronx Expressway. The decals would portray neat drapery, flowerpots, and window boxes, intimations of comfortable and happy domestic scenes. That way, commuters who passed through the Bronx en route to Westchester, Long Island, or the Connecticut executive belt wouldn't have to be upset by the sight of the misery that lines their way.--Marshall Berman. Roots, Ruins, Renewals: City Life After Urbicide, Village Voice, September 4, 1984
    Potemkin was a Russian statesman who had an impressive, fake village built along the river bank in preparation for a tour by Catherine the Great. The village consisted of just the facades of houses which were removed after she passed by and then reassembled further down river. Thus as Catherine traveled by, she would see many pleasant villages with happy peasants and think all was well in her kingdom.--Mel Rosenthal
  - East on 173rd Street (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0003)
  - Going to church on a Sunday morning (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0004)
  - [Three young women of color in front of burned out buildings] (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0005)
    One of the high school students told me she was going to be a dental assistant. The other two said they wanted to be models.
  - Mother and daughter, Claremont Parkway (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0006)
    The South Bronx is certain to be one of the areas hardest hit by the President's [Nixon] decision to impose austerity on domestic programs presumably in order to pay the brutal costs of a senseless war [Vietnam]. Combined with state budgetary restraints the outlook is bleak, for the South Bronx is dependent on public resources, not just for the quality of life, but for life itself.--Mayor John Lindsay, New York Times, January 18, 1973
    We should not encourage people to stay where their job possibilities are becoming daily more remote...Our urban system is based on the theory of taking the peasant and turning him into an industrial worker. Now there are no industrial jobs. Why not keep him a peasant?--Roger Starr, Real Estate Weekly, February 9, 1976
    It can only be compared to war, what happened here, and we lost that war.--Father Louis Gigante, Associated Press, October 5, 1977
  - Bathgate Avenue (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0007)
  - Sisters on Bathgate Avenue (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0008)
  - Mother and daughter, East 173rd Street (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0009)
  - [Group portrait of African American churchgoers, standing in front of the church] (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0010)
    The African American churches, many of which had been synagogues, were a bulwark against the encroaching disintegration.
  - [Two young boys playing baseball in the street] (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0011)
    The kids played baseball using the parking meter as second base. The runner was safe.
  - The daily domino game in front of the Social Club (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0012)
  - [Man with bayonet] (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0013)
    He said, "Want a ghetto shot? I'll give you a ghetto shot!" And he drew a bayonet from under his jacket.
  - [Young man crouching on roof top with dog] (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0014)
    It was the day that the last building on Bathgate Avenue was being sealed up before demolition. The city marshals were evicting all the remaining families. Nelson's family was being sent to an apartment where no dogs were allowed. He knew that if the dog ended up in the pound, he'd be "put away." We couldn't find a home for the dog. Many of the people who were being evicted were supposed to go to a "welfare hotel." There were no other options. People were scared and depressed.
  - South Bronx site of the 1980 "People's Convention" in opposition to the Democratic Party's nominating convention downtown (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0015)
  - On Bathgate Avenue where the fire hydrant functioned as the community's well (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0016)
    Your business will have room to grow in the Bronx. You don't have to worry about spiraling rents, lack of space, congested streets, parking shortages, and a host of other problems that plague expanding businesses elsewhere. The Bronx has prime real estate that is affordable. No inflated prices like Westchester, New Jersey, or Long Island. The City of New York is planning to sell prime parcels of real estate for retail, light manufacturing, office and industrial development. These are properties which the city has held from sale until the market was right. Now the market is right. You can own real estate in thriving, busy commercial centers, industrial enclaves, and growing residential areas.--The Bronx: Business's Best Kept Secret, Published by the Bronx Marketing Project, NYC Department of General Services, 1985
  - [Naked doll in foreground of a demolished lot, a burned out building in background] (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0017)
    The last building left standing in the neighborhood was on the East 173rd through 174th Street block. A few days after this picture was made, the building was bulldozed and the people who lived there were sent to shelters and single room occupancy hotels.
  - Bathgate Avenue, South Bronx, NY [Woman of color in white dress, striking a pose in the street] (Box 3, Image RL10011-P-0018)
    When I looked for her to give her the picture, her building had burned and she had moved.
  - [Brick building with three billboards] (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0019)
  - Paulina and her dog, Bathgate Avenue (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0020)
  - [Pregnant woman at obstetrician visit, listening to her own baby's heartbeat] (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0021)
  - [Aerial shot of South Bronx streets] (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0022)
  - [Man who left the neighborhood years ago, but came back for drinks every Friday evening] (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0023)
  - [Mikey at the bar, next to Rosenthal's photographs] (Box 1, Image RL10011-P-0024)
  - [A close up of an older man and two young men, seated in alley] (Box 2, Image RL10011-P-25)
  - [Girl running in street, in front of demolished building, covering her mouth] (Box 2, Image RL10011-P-26)
  - [Teenage boy walking out of a burned out building with a bicycle] (Box 2, Image RL10011-P-27)
  - St. Athanasia's baseball team (Box 2, Image RL10011-P-28)
  - [Boy in front of demolished building, hands in the pocket of jacket] (Box 2, Image RL10011-P-29)
  - [Boy in front of demolished building, hands in the pocket of jacket] (Box 2, Image RL10011-P-30)
    Duplicate of image 29, but this print is signed by Rosenthal.
  - [Father and daughter in living room, girl standing in front of television, dad in armchair] (Box 2, Image RL10011-P-31)
  - Fourth of July, hanging out on the stoop of their apartment house (Box 2, Image RL10011-P-32)
  - Mel Rosenthal in his old bedroom in the South Bronx (Box 2, Image RL10011-P-33)
- The Arab-Americans: Americans by Choice, 2000-2002; 2 boxes
  Contains 46 photographs, 25 16x20" (with one 11x14") gelatin silver prints (box 4) and 21 11x14" gelatin silver prints (box 5), that were part of the exhibit Arab-Americans: American By Choice. The images document the daily lives of Arabic-speaking Americans, many of whom were in New York State at the time the shots were taken. The individuals portrayed include men, women, and children of Syrian, Egyptian, Moroccan, Algerian, Jordanian and Palestinian descent. Scenes include the religious life of Christians, Muslims, Greek Orthodox, Maronites, Jews and Coptics.
  - Halal food stand in lower Manhattan, NY, 2001 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-34)
    Ahmed was from Alexandria, Egypt. He decided to go back to Egypt in September of 2002 to get married. His friends, including the man who bought his cart, thought that he would not be able to get a visa to come back to the United States. They were correct and as one said, Another man lost.
  - B&B Electronics store owner showing photographs of himself and his daughter in East Jerusalem (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-35)
    One of the reasons he left Jerusalem was because of the 1967 war. He told me that he believed that the war between the Israelis and the Arabs would never end. He is holding a photo of him holding his baby daughter. Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, N.Y., 1998.
  - Roller blading Palestinian teenager (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-36)
    She is the daughter of Essa (see image 35) who is holding her (as a baby) before the family left East Jerusalem
  - Astroland Amusement Park, Coney Island, N.Y., 1999 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-37)
    Men observe the call to prayer, March 27, 1999. The occasion is Eid al-Fitr the three-day Festival of Fast-Breaking at the end of Ramadan.
  - Eid al Fitr, Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, 2000 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-38)
    Men observe the call to prayer, 2001. The occasion is Eid al-Fitr the three-day Festival of Fast-Breaking at the end of Ramadan.
  - Moroccan Jews celebrating Chanukah at the Manhattan Sephardic Center, N.Y., 2001 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-39)
    I showed the Rabbi a letter of introduction from the Museum of the City of New York which said that they had commissioned me to photograph for them an exhibition about Arab American life in New York. They told me that I was in the wrong place because they were not Arabs. They insisted that they were Sephardic and should be called that. I pointed out to them that they spoke Arabic and were from a country which spoke Arabic and therefore could be considered Arabs. They weren't convinced, but it turned out that they did not have the tenth Jewish man that makes a ritual possible in the Jewish religion and there I was, the tenth man. So I got to celebrate Chanukah and to photograph them also. Later because so many people took umbrage to being called an Arab I changed the letter to say that I was photographing Arabic speaking people and thus avoided problems. As with the case of many of the Christian Arabic speaking people, many seem to equate "Arab" with being Muslim and they did not want to be associated with that identification. September 11th made that even more pronounced.
  - Moroccan and Algerian Muslims at a community mosque in a tent at Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, N.Y., 2002 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-40)
  - Woman, child and icon, Church of the Virgin Mary, Palm Sunday, Brooklyn, 2001 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-41)
    The Church in Park Slope is a Greek-Melkite Catholic Church and the icon is St. Theodora. The people at the Church when I spoke to them about why I was photographing there they like the told me that they were not Arabs and were annoyed that I called them that. I asked them what they called themselves and they said they were Phoenicians. Having learned from the Moroccans, I said it was fine, and that this was a project about Arabic speaking people. I looked up Phoenicia in an Encyclopedia and they had a drawing of where Phoenicia had been and it was what now is Syria and Lebanon.
  - Midday prayers at the Al Noor School, Sunset Park, Brooklyn, N.Y., 2001 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-42)
    The school has students whose parents come from all of the countries in the world with Muslim populations. The students are segregated by gender and most of the curriculum is in Arabic since that is the language of the Koran. Boys and girls are forbidden to speak to each other. If they do the boy is chastised, but the girl may be put on probation or expelled. When I was photographing there the text being studied in the English class was Exodus, by Leon Uris.
  - Girls playing basketball in the schoolyard of the Al Noor School, 2002 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-43)
  - Young Syrian American girl who goes to the local public school in Brooklyn Heights (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-44)
    I was told by one of the teachers that the school has many students who come from Arabic speaking countries. Muslims, Christians, Jews and people who profess no particular religion all coexist well there.
  - Young Syrian American girl who goes to the local public school in Brooklyn Heights (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-45)
    A 11x14" duplicate of RL10011-P-44.
  - Sizing a Palestinian wedding dress, Brooklyn, N.Y., 1998 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-46)
    A fitting at Four Golden Needles, a dress shop in Bay Ridge Brooklyn which was created and owned by four Palestinian women. The woman trying on the dress is from Lebanon and the dressmaker is from Egypt. The material was designed on the computer and then printed out on the textile machine in the background. The dress was shipped to a woman getting married in Chicago.
  - Bride, groom and the groom's mother at the wedding in Widdi's Catering Hall, Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, N.Y., 1999 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-47)
    Celebrating the wedding of Sandra Hajjaj and Komenby Kharoufeh. The groom's mother is trying to keep the playing children from colliding with the cake.
  - Palestinian American Women at a wedding in Widdi's Catering Hall, Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, N.Y., 1999 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-48)
    Widdi's is known throughout the Arab American community as the place to have your party after Ramadan, your wedding, your confirmation party, your fund raising party, or your political meeting of the community. Gold coins are traditional wedding presents which are pinned to the bride's dress at the marriage ceremony. It is common for the women to wear strings of gold coins minted in the Mid-East around their heads and their waists on special occasions such as this wedding. One man when I asked about it said that we don't trust banks.
  - A relative of the groom dancing at the wedding in Widdi's Catering Hall, Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, NY, 1999 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-49)
    He is the spitting image of one my cousins when we were younger. As I looked around the room filled with Palestinians it struck me that many of the people there looked like my own relatives and I thought how come they can't see it. They are from the same family. When will they see it. When will the killings stop!
  - Astroland Amusement Park, Coney Island, NY, 1999 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-50)
    I liked this photograph, but it was not in the exhibition of my work, because the museum directors thought it inflammatory. I thought they were being overly cautious, but it was soon after the attack on the towers and many people were upset and so I lost the argument.
  - Ecumenical Peace March of Christians, Moslems and Jews, Bay Ridge, Brooklyn Sept. 26, 2001 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-51)
    Over a thousand Christians, Muslims, and Jewish Arab Americans made clear their desire for peace and their hatred for violence. Unfortunately, though the Churches, Mosques and Synagogues sent out many press releases, none of the press came to report about this event.
  - Peace vigil on the Esplanade, Brooklyn Heights, N.Y., Sept 16, 2001 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-52)
    Debbie Almontaser, an educator and activist, carried a photograph of her son wherever she went. He was in the National Guard patrolling the area around Ground Zero and couldn't go to the Peace Vigil, September 16, 2001. After September 11th a number of people in Brooklyn Heights called her names and tried to get her to take off her hijab. She started to carry the photograph of her son who had been called up to the National Guard on September 11th. She told the people that were harassing her that he was in the National Guard patrolling the area around Ground Zero and that she was as patriotic as they were. She told me that the harassment was so bad that teachers at the public school where she worked had to escort her to school and back. Shortly after, she resigned from teaching there.
  - Muhaideen Batah and Yosef Thalen in Brooklyn, N.Y., 1999 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-53)
    Muhaideen (with camera) was one of my students who became one of my friends. He received his Bachelors Degree from the State University of New York/Empire State College. He was a photography major who was a carpenter years ago in Nazareth, and is now is a successful photographer and lecturer on Palestinian and Islamic issues and lives in Vermont. Yosef, lived in Jerusalem and Jordan most of the time and made a living by coming to Brooklyn and selling tiny Korans on the streets and in the mosques. When he was in Brooklyn he slept in one of the Mosques. He died in 2004.
  - Palestinian woman (older) with candle at peace vigil (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-54)
    There was a march of more than a thousand people of all denominations against violence in Brooklyn Heights. The press did not carry it to any extent.
  - Josef Thalen (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-55)
    He said he was saluting the King of Jordan.
  - Her brother was still missing, Peace March, September 26, 2001 (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-56)
  - Patriarch looking at a photograph of a woman who is searching for her brother who has probably been killed by the attack on the twin towers (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-57)
  - Iraqi Woman student at an English as a Second Language Class, Utica, N.Y. (Box 4, Image RL10011-P-58)
  - [Dr. Alrawi, an Iraqi OB/GYN doctor, has a "wellness" practice for women in Bay Ridge, Brooklyn] (Box 5, Image RL10011-P-59)
    Her pregnant patient is from Aden, 2004.
  - Carrying a Greek orthodox cross at the march against violence and terrorism on Bay Ridge Blvd. (Box 5, Image RL10011-P-60)
  - Doha working in the pastry bakery "The International Gourmet Delight" that she and her husband own (Box 5, Image RL10011-P-61)